Hello. In this session, we would like to introduce the opensource contributhon
as a way to increase new participants or contributors to open source in Korea.
There are 3 presenters including myself for this presentation.
First, let me introduce myself.
My name is Bok-mi Han, who works for an organization called the National IT Industry Promotion Agency of Korea
and is the leader of the open source promotion team. Nice to see you.
In this session, I would like to introduce the background of the promotion of the Opensource Contributhon and the current status of its activities.
The second presenter is Youngbin Han, who is the representative of the Ubuntu Korean Community, and is participating in UbuCon Asia 2021 preparations.
He will share with you the experience of participating as a mentor for the Ubuntu Korean Translation team at the Opensource Contributhon last year.
The third and final presenter is Joowon Jung, who is a computer science graduate. She is a member of the Ubuntu Korean community and active on the Ubuntu Korean translation team.
She will share her experience as a mentee for the Ubuntu Korean Translation team at the Opensource Contributhon last year.
First, let me introduce about the Opensource Contributhon.
The word "Contributhon" may sound unfamiliar.
"Contributhon", which is the compound word of Contribution and Marathon,
is the program where  a mentor, who is a senior developer, and a number of mentees form a team
and the mentee can directly experience the opensource culture by contributing in a variety of ways.
During the Contributhon process, 1~3 mentors and 15 mentees perform the mission together for 6 weeks.
Contributhon activities were offline before COVID-19, but now are mainly online meetings.
I has been found that having at least the first one or two times to network with each other between teammates through offline meetings
rather than online meetings is very important.
I will explain the Contributhon operating process.
To explain the ,
at first, select the projects and mentors, and then recruit mentees,
and the next 6 weeks the team work on, finally hold the awards ceremony.
Let me explain in a little more detail.
First, We call for OSS projects and mentors then select among them for Contributhon.
Any opensource project can apply for participation.
Opensource experts select 25 projects to participate in through screening.
Second, We call for mentees who will participate for selected OSS projects then select among them.
This year, about 370 mentees were selected, and the competition was very high.
Third, mentors and mentees form the teams and start 6 weeks of activities with the kick-off ceremony.
Through 6 weeks of mentoring, mentees learn to contribute and grow together.
Fourth, at the end, each team share the 6-week activities,
and all mentors evaluate together to select and announce the best team.
These programs have been promoted by Ministry of Science and ICT and National IT Industry Promotion Agency in Korea since 2016.
Next, I'll tell you about the purpose of the Opensource Contributhon.
Contributhon values “how” rather than “what” and “process” rather than “product”.
It is the natural spirit of open source, and mentors mentor how to contribute these natural things.
In particular,
they engage in various contribution activities such as
code review, bug reporting, questions, issues, comments, suggestions, and documentation.
A lot of developer or student in Korea are developing using opensource.
However, there are still very few people who contribute beyond just using opensource.
Contributon wants to share and spread the open source development culture and value of contribution
to participants who have not yet contributed.
Contributhon consists of the mentors, the mentees, and the projects.
Of course, we can’t forget the Contributhon Secretariat,
which helps the Contributhon run well in an invisible place .
Mentors are the opensource experts,
who plays the role of  project contributor, committer, maintainer, or owner at the opensource projects, and are the teachers of the mentees.
About one to three mentors are on  a team,
and most of them are employees belonging to companies and are very busy with their work.
However, they participated with a passion for opensource.
Most mentees are junior developers or students
who are interested in opensource but have never participated.
Through this opportunity, they get to know new people and learn new things very seriously.
About 10 to 15 mentees participate in a team, and most try to complete,
but some fail to complete, so the completion rate is about 80%.
There are cases in which the mentee grows and participates as a mentor in the next year.
Each project is a project in which mentors are active,
including development projects or translation projects.
Any OSS project that wants to increase its contributors can be said to be a target.
The screen you see now shows the projects and companies in which the mentors who have participated so far have been active.
They are participating in Contributhon in various projects such as
the well-known OpenStack, Keras, Linux Kernel, RosettaStone, Apache Zeppelin, Armeria, Tizen, and Ethereum Foundation projects.
As is the global trend, AI-related projects are also popular in Korea recently.
In addition, not only development projects, but also projects for Korean translation are involved.
In Korea, Korean translation is also very important to increase opensource participation.
There are some cases that each OSS project operate its own contributhon now.
It is a very desirable phenomenon for a civilian project to take care of what the government started and do it on their own.
Like this, developers and companies in Korea are making great efforts to increase the number of open source participants.
This slide shows the history of Contributhon,
which has been promoted annually for 6 years from 2016 to present 2021.
As you can see on the previous page, about 85 projects were involved,
131 mentors and 1169 mentees participated.
As you can see from the graph on the right,
the number of participants is increasing every year.
As such, it is being promoted with the interest of many people.
This year, 25 projects, 50 mentors, and 373 mentees participate, making it the largest ever.
This is the history of Contributhon's activities.
Before COVID-19, we gathered and held kickoffs, contribution activity meetings, awards ceremony, etc. offline.
But since COVID-19, we are doing it online.
This year, the kick-off was held on the metaverse platform, GatherTown.
It was fun and a new experience for me
to see about 400 people gather in Gather Town and move around.
However, I miss having everyone gather together and start offline as before.
Contribution activities are conducted by teams and led by mentors.
They meet online or offline about once a week and work together.
At the awards ceremony, each team's contribution activities are announced,
and excellent teams are selected based on the evaluation of mentors.
Excellent teams are awarded the Minister's Award from Ministry of Science and ICT,
which establishes and promotes open source policies,
and the Director's Award from National IT Industry Promotion Agency.
This year is 6 years since Contributon started, and this year there is a new change.
It has been expanded to the contribution academy.
The short period of 6 weeks became a lot of pressure for the mentors,
so we increased it to 4 months and lowered the burden on the mentors.
We also strengthened the basics as an academy.
Basic education such as Github usage education for junior developers has been added,
Mentors for each team can focus on mentoring opensource projects.
Mentees were able to directly participate in team activities through basic training.
And by dividing Challenges program and Masters program,
the opportunities for mentees to participate were diversified.
In the Challenges program, mentees learn basic courses such as Github
and perform basic missions for each project, such as build and environment setting for about a month.
In the Masters program, after completing the challenge program,
team collaboration development activities are carried out
through regular mentoring of mentors for about 3 months.
This year, we are having fun with this new Contributhon.
In this page, I will introduce the open source promotion activities of the National IT Industry Promotion Agency, NIPA, which is promoting Contributhon.
NIPA is Korea's IT and software development promotion agency along with the Ministry of Science and ICT.
In particular, NIPA's opensource promotion team supports various activities for Korean opensource developers, communities, and companies.
First, we are doing an Open Frontier or Contributhon business for open source developers.
To support community activities, we support holding seminars and meetings,
Due to COVID-19, we are currently supporting mainly online events.
In addition, we support opensource governance consulting for companies
such as opensource compliance and license,
and help companies establish opensource strategies.
We hold open source conferences every year
to share information or create a forum for developers, communities, and companies to communicate.
This year, it will be held online at the end of November, and about 30 sessions are being prepared.
In addition, we are operating the OpenUp Center as a space where open source developers and communities can come and work at any time.
Lastly, we have developed a Linux-based open OS for desktop
and are distributing it for use by the government and the private sector.
In this way, NIPA is providing various support for the opensource ecosystem.
So I hope for a lot of interest.
This figures are OpenUp center established to support open source integration.
There is a development space, meeting space, seminar or education, and relaxation space,
Opensource developers, communities, contributors, etc. can conveniently visit and use it at any time.
So far, I have given you a general description of Contributhon,
so please feel free to contact me with any questions you may have
In the next part, Youngbin Han, who actually participated as a mentor at Contributhon,
will share her participation experience.
Hello, from now on, I would like to talk about my experience participating as a mentor
for the Ubuntu Korean Translation Team at the Opensource Contributhon last year.
The Ubuntu Korean Community has been running a translation team
to translate packages included in Ubuntu for a long time.
As those of you who have participated in Ubuntu translation are well aware,
we have been contributing to Ubuntu translation through Launchpad.
As with other opensources, there are always new contributors,
and there are many who stop contributing in the middle.
There are many people who are new to contributing voluntarily,
but there are many who do not know,
and many who do not know how to start.
So, in order to help those who are new to Ubuntu translation get a good start,
we regularly do documentation and hold workshop events for them.
In the past, before the spread of COVID-19, workshop events were often held like this photo.
In addition to Ubuntu translation, we often held workshops on various topics
such as Debian packaging and the Internet of Things.
Through various workshop events,
we used to help people who want to contribute to Ubuntu for the first time to get started easily.
Usually, these workshop events were planned and held in the form of holding a one-day schedule,
which is similar to the workshop sessions at large conference events.
In offline workshop events, participants usually take their time to participate,
they have the advantage of being able to learn well by focusing more on the practice
and they can get help right away for parts they don't know or find difficult.
However, this one-day workshop event has some limitations.
Contributors can start contributing more easily
compared to when they started contributing alone,
but usually they only contribute for a short period of time, such as a few days or months, after participating in the event,
and then stop contributing.
For this reason, it is rare for those who started contributing through workshop participation
to become long-term contributors by continuing to contribute.
And since last year, it is difficult to hold offline events due to the spread of COVID-19.
Due to social distancing,
it was impossible to hold an offline event with a large number of people,
so it was necessary to move offline activities online.
Meanwhile, last year, I joined the Opensource Contributhon as a mentor for the first time.
I had heard of this event before participating in the Opensource Contributhon,
so I knew about it and was interested.
However, it was difficult for me to participate because I was serving in the military.
After completing my military service last year,
I joined it at the request of other organizers.
So, for a longer period of six weeks, we were able to be with these who first to participate in the Ubuntu translation.
Since the opensource contributhon I participated in last year was the activity after the spread of COVID-19,
I also had the opportunity to think about
how to continue offline activities online after the spread of COVID-19.
Fortunately, last summer, there was a time when offline meetings were possible for a short time,
so the 6-week Contributhon activities started with the offline initiation ceremony.
After the kick-off ceremony, training was conducted for mentees,
which is similar to the translation workshop we've done before.
The picture you see now is a picture I took while training for the mentees.
We've provided training and hands-on training from how to sign up for Launchpad, to sign up for Ubuntu's Code of Conduct with your GPG key,
and to submit translation suggestions.
Contributing as a translation, if you speak English well,
is relatively easy to get started with, compared to contributing by writing code.
Becuase all you have to do is sign up for the launchpad, choose the packages you want to translate,
and fill out and submit a translation proposal.
There is no program to install, and you can start right from the web.
There is no need to study a new programming language or technology in particular,
or to analyze existing source code.
But as easy as it is to start, it can quickly become boring and tiring.
Because if you contribute to opensource through development, you can contribute by checking if there is any problem with your work,
but most of the UI translation is a repetitive task of translating short or long English strings.
Since Ubuntu translation from the launchpad usually submited directly from the web,
it is difficult to check whether the translation is natural in the actual program.
There are many cases where it is not possible to fully translate a single package.
Sometimes it's because there are too many strings included in the package,
sometimes the included strings are constantly changing,
or the package no longer needs to be translated, because it was deprecated.
Those who start contributing translations for the first time do not take this into account
and many of them focus only on translating a large amount of strings in a short time,
and then give up after getting tired of it.
In Contributhon, it is not important to achieve results in a short period of time,
but to help mentees finish without getting tired for a long period of time.
There are a few things we've introduced to help them get to the finish line.
First, we had them set individual weekly translation goals.
Mentors and mentees often each have their own work, such as study or company work,
and each has a different amount of time to invest in opensource contributions.
It is not important to do a lot of translation,
but it is more important to accurately translate even a small amount of translation,
and to continuously translate and manage changed strings.
By setting a goal for the number of strings that can be translated per week,
and allowing each mentee to translate as much as their goal,
the burden of contributing to translation was reduced,
and mentees did not get tired quickly.
As with other Linux distributions,
Ubuntu has an innumerable variety of packages,
and all of them are subject to translation.
However, of course, not all packages can be translated,
so we divided the participating mentees into small teams
so that each team can choose one to four packages and focus on translating them.
By setting up a mentor for each team and providing translation feedback for each team,
the mentee's burden on translation proposals and the mentee's translation review burden were reduced,
helping to make better translations.
In order for the mentees to do well until the end,
it would be very helpful to provide feedback and let them know if they are doing well.
As mentioned earlier,
due to the nature of Ubuntu translation,
which usually submits translations directly through the launchpad on the web,
it is not easy to check whether the translation is natural in the actual program
before submitting the translation.
That's why it's important to provide frequent feedback.
At Contributhon, we had to submit a midterm report,
so there were times to check whether the mentees were doing well.
Usually, while reviewing translation proposals,
we sometimes provide feedback on incorrect translations
or translations that can be improved.
We helped them by asking questions even when they were not sure how to translate,
and also shared about common translation mistakes, various translation conventions,
the translation rules of the Ubuntu Korean Translation Team, and glossary.
Opensource Contributhon is not only a mentoring program, but also a competition.
So, at the end, the performance of each project was announced, evaluated, and awards were given.
It felt a little new to me to evaluate and give awards in the mentoring program.
When presenting and evaluating the performance, mentors for each project participated in the evaluation,
and I participated in the Ubuntu Korean Translation Team.
All of the mentees for each project have very good presentations and the results were so good that
it was difficult to evaluate which project came out better.
The performance presentation was a short time of 5 minutes for each team,
but since there are many teams presenting,
it must have been very difficult to sit down for a long time and concentrate on the presentations of the mentees.
Through Contributhon, I was able to meet new mentees who wanted to contribute to Ubuntu translation,
and working with mentees for a long time, we were able to significantly improve the quality of Ubuntu translation.
The result was remarkably good.
First, some of the mentees were ranked among the top 20 contributors
to the launchpad translation.
Translations contributed by mentees were reviewed by mentors,
and were immediately reflected in Ubuntu 20.10,
which was released after the period of activity.
While participating in Contributhon,
I thought about what could be improved in the operation of the translation team.
The Ubuntu Korean translation team document is well documented
on the translation rules and translation methods,
but there is a problem in a place that is not easy to find for those
who want to contribute to the translation for the first time.
I thought we should improve the documentation to make it easier to find.
We also thought of improving the documentation on
how to actually test what a translation will look like before submitting a translation suggestion
so we can get a better translation.
So far, I've talked about my experience as a mentor
to Opensource Contributhon last year.
Next, Joowon Jung will tell you about her experience as a mentee for the Ubuntu Korean Translation project.
Hello, I would like to present my experience as a mentee
for the 2020 Opensource Contributhon Ubuntu Korean Translation Project.
I heard the word opensource a lot when I was in college,
but I didn't know exactly what it was.
Distributed free of charge, and anyone can modify it and redistribute it.
I just understood it that way.
In the meantime, through a class called Introduction To Opeonsource Software,
I became interested in open source software.
Through the research assignment on opensource trends,
I learned that opensource software also has licenses
and that open source software mainly grows with the community,
and my interest in opensource software grew.
Of course, I was just interested in it rather than making any contribution.
While looking for various information about open source software,
I came across various developer communities,
and in the meantime I came across an activity called Opensource Contributhon.
I was interested in hearing that it was an activity where I could contribute to an opensource project
with the help of senior developers who participated as mentors.
Getting information about various opensource software,
I thought that I would like to contribute to an opensource project someday,
but I was hesitant about how to contribute to which project
and where and how to start and was unable to start anything.
So this activity came as a great opportunity for me.
Even though I am interested in any open source project,
I have no idea how to start even after reading the guide page for new contributors,
and even the Best First Issue, which is left as an issue that beginners can contribute, feels difficult.
However, by participating in the Opensource Contributhon,
it seemed that it would be easier to contribute with the help of senior developers.
Looking around the various opensource projects participating in the Opensource Contributhon,
I thought about which project it would be better to participate in,
but I chose the Ubuntu Korean Translation project and applied for it.
I felt that my development ability was still insufficient
to contribute to an opensource project through coding,
so I thought it would be good to start contributing as a translation project.
And as a Ubuntu user,
I wanted to participate in an opensource project for the operating system I use on a daily basis.
I applied for the Ubuntu Korean translation project and was selected as a mentee,
and I started Contributhon activities for 6 weeks.
Contributhon activities started with hearing about the Ubuntu Korean translation project
and joining the Ubuntu Korean Translation team.
Since the Ubuntu Korean Translation project is being conducted on a platform called Launchpad, we joined Launchpad.
In the process, we generated a GPG key and signed the Code of Conduct, etc.
It is the first time to generate a GPG key and to do an electronic signature through it.
Even this is unfamiliar,
so if I had started it by myself rather than participating Contributhon,
I think I would have lost my way here.
Still, the mentors explained to us step by step and guided us
so that we would not give up while wandering in unfamiliar tasks,
so we were able to do it without difficulty.
To join the Ubuntu Korean translation team,
you need to sign up for the launchpad, subscribe to the Ubuntu Korean translation team mailing,
and accumulate at least 50 karma.
Karma can be seen as an activity score on the Launchpad,
which can be accumulated through contribution activities on the Launchpad,
and disappears after a long period of time,
so it indicate the amount of activity of the contributor.
Even if not joined the Ubuntu Korean translation team,
you can build karma through translation suggestions,
so we took the time to make a translation suggestion
to get karma for joining the Ubuntu Korean Translation team.
In a situation where we cannot meet often due to COVID-19,
time to apply for a member of the Ubuntu Korean Translation Team
and practice translation proposals by meeting offline
was an important first step in translation activities during the 6-week Contributhon period.
During that time by asking questions to the mentors,
we got used to the unfamiliar platform called Launchpad
and learned how to translate activities there.
At first, there were a lot of trivial questions like
"Is this right?", "Is it correct to press this button?",
gradually we got used to it and were able to do it on our own.
After applying to join the Ubuntu Korean translation team and practicing translation proposals in offline training,
we have been translating online in the time we can contribute in our daily lives.
Translation work was performed on various packages
Depending on the package, for some packages,
it is easier to understand the context by
specifying where the text exists in which file in the package's git repository.
However, in other packages, it was difficult to translate
because it was impossible to know in what context the text was used.
At times, I was not sure whether this expression was interpreted in this way in this context.
When I asked a question through the Contributhon channel of Ubuntu Korean Community Slack,
the mentors thought about it together and suggested an appropriate translation,
so it went smoothly to do translation work.
Even if not a question, there were cases when the translated sentences were not smooth,
receiving feedback from mentors to refine the expression.
In addition, in selecting which package to translate among numerous packages,
as a reference when selecting a package to translate,
the mentors recommended packages with a low translation rate even though they were major packages.
So we were able to do many translations focusing on packages that users need more.
The biggest stumbling block I felt while activities was that
I couldn't see any noticeable results.
Unlike adding functions or fixing bugs in software, the results of the activities are not immediately visible.
Rather, the translation rate is only increasing little by little,
but that small increase was difficult to act as a meaningful motivator.
Afterwards, when the translated content was reflected in the Ubuntu distribution,
I felt glad when I encountered  the packages I translated,
but during the Contributethon, the visibility of the activity was greatly reduced
because it had not yet been reflected in the Ubuntu distribution.
And the difficult-to-translate texts we often encounter acted as another stumbling block.
If the git repository path is listed,
I first translated it by inferring the context,
and if it was not resolved,
I took the method of asking questions to the mentors.
Of course, there were cases where the text remained difficult to translate.
In that case, it would be more beneficial to try to translate another text
than to hold on to it, so I passed.
In the case of an unfamiliar package that I did not normally use,
I was hesitant to translate it
because I did not have prior knowledge about the package,
but through a search, I was able to translate it better
by figuring out the context of what the package does.
Certain proper nouns and verbs used within the package
were judged to be transliterated as foreign words.
Sometimes the text to be translated contains an abbreviation
but it is difficult to know what the abbreviation is.
Depending on the package, there are cases where it is written
so that I can refer to what it stands for,
but there are cases where it is not.
Abbreviations that can be inferred or appear immediately after searching
could be interpreted and translated as they are,
but there were cases where it was the first abbreviation I had ever seen
and I did not understand it even if I searched.
Sometimes I couldn't figure it out, so I passed it,
but the abbreviation found in another package showed what it means,
and I realized later that the one I had seen before seemed to have the same meaning.
After six weeks of Contributhon work, we looked back at our achievements.
On the day we met offline and joined the Ubuntu Korean translation team,
we set a goal for each of our translation activities.
When we checked how much we had achieved compared to the goal,
some mentees translated several times the target amount,
but some mentees did not reach the goal sufficiently.
During the contribution period,
a total of 4,636 translation contributions were made by us,
and two of us including myself were ranked among the top 20
in the translation category of the TOP contributors ranking,
which ranked the contributions of Ubuntu contributors worldwide.
Our translations were reflected in the Ubuntu 20.10 Groovy Gorilla version
released after the Contributhon activity ended.
It's meaningful to me as a Ubuntu user and as a contributor to the translation activity
that many Ubuntu Korean users can use packages we translated.
There were mentees who expressed their intention to continue to participate in the Ubuntu Korean Translation project even after the contributhon period was over.
and some of them actually continued their translation activities even after the end of their official activities,
resulting in continuous Ubuntu Korean Translation contributors.
Of course, there were a few things that were disappointing.
As it is a project in which each individual translates independently rather than collaborating with someone else,
there is an advantage in that each of them can work independently and voluntarily at a convenient time
without difficulty in time coordination and communication.
But There were aspects of it that were not very well motivating
because there is almost no communication between mentees and only repeating similar translation work alone.
I heard that some mentees, before the start of the contributhon activity, applied for this project in expect that
the activity of translating the applications' man page
rather than translating the text of the operating system utility
due to lack of understanding of the Ubuntu Korean translation project.
This feeling of disparity between expectations and reality may served as one of the reasons
why some mentees did not fully reach their goals for translation activities.
I think about how it would have been if I had personally jumped into the path of a contributor
to the Ubuntu Korean Translation project
by myself without participating in the opensource contributhon.
Even the process of signing up for Launchpad and joining the Ubuntu Korean Translation team must have gone through a lot.
Even after joining the Ubuntu Korean translation team,
I pondered whether it was right to submit this like this, or whether it was appropriate to translate it like this in this situation,
and I think that I may have given up after not long in the end.
Of course, in such a case, there is a community where I can leave a question,
and I could have moved forward with the help of such a community,
but having someone you can ask a question comfortably
is a big help when you apply for a bill in an unfamiliar field.
Participating in the Opensource Contributhon Ubuntu Korean Translation project last year,
I felt that my experience of contributing to the opensource project was very meaningful and rewarding.
So this year, I am participating in Opensource Contribution Academy,
which was reorganized Opensource Contributhon.
This time, I applied to the RustPython project to challenge the contribution through coding.
These days, I have been busy with various things, so I haven't been active since last June,
but when I have time again, I will try to contribute to the Ubuntu Korean Translation project again in my spare time.
This concludes the presentation. Thank you.