Hello everyone, I am Burgess Chang from the Ubuntu Kylin community
The topic sharing I brought to you today is
how to promote the localization of the ethnic minority languages of China on Ubuntu
The first words are a simple self-introduction
My name is Burgess Chang,and I am from Ubuntu Kylin Community and KDE Network China
I usually like and care about FOSS very much
I am a user of Ubuntu, Ubuntu Kylin ,Fedora and ArchLinux
The reason why I use Linux is because I need to use them for development work and package work
I usually use C, C++, Python, Rust and Lisp for my programming development work
This demo environment uses ArchLinux and GNU Emacs
Then you can contact me through these two emails
At the beginning of this topic sharing
I hope to briefly introduce the situation of ethnic minorities in China
China has 56 ethnicities
55 of which are ethnic minorities
Fifty-three of them have their own language and character system
Promoting a stabilization of their own language on ubuntu can
help protect the cultural and historical heritage of Chinese ethnic minorities
This is also the core aim of our project at the beginning
according to my personal understanding
I think that the multilingual support of all operating systems is an element of core concern
For the ethnic minority languages of China
such as Windows, macOS, Android, iOS, they all have different degrees of support
According to my personal understanding, in China's Xinjiang province,
ethnic minorities prefer to use macOS and iOS
because macOS and iOS have a better Uyghur-Chinese language support
Then in China's Inner Mongolia, everyone may prefer to use Windows
Because Mongolian-Chinese language support of Windows is relatively good
And relatively, the Chinese ethnic minorities multilingual support on Linux is a relatively weak part
For example, Manchu-Chinese language, Mongolian-Chinese language, Uyghur-Chinese language, Tibetan-Chinese and Zhuang-Chinese Language
are all very incomplete support status on Linux
This is also the status quo of our project
Our work started at the beginning of 2020
The main thing is to add an experimental support to the Tibetan-Chinese language on Ubuntu Kylin
Because Ubuntu Kylin is an official flavor of Ubuntu
these work are also applicable to Ubuntu
Then, regarding our localization work
I would like to express my gratitude for the help and support of some people from Information Science and Technology college of Tibetan University
They are Professor ཉི་མ་བཀྲ་ཤིས། , Professor རིག་འཛིན་རྡོ་རྗེ། , Professor བསོད་ནམས་རྒྱ་མཚོ།
and འཇམ་དབྱངས་རྒྱལ། , བསམ་འཕེལ་ཚེ་རིང་། , etc
.In the following words, I would like to introduce to you the current situation of Ubuntu localization in Tibetan-Chinese language
At present, the support for the localization of Tibetan-Chinese language
on ubuntu and Ubuntu Kylin is relatively limited
Then I wrote a list of support here
First of all, regarding the supported distributions,
there are Ubuntu and Ubuntu Kylin
Then the covery versions include Ubuntu 16.04 and 20.04
and there are also Ubuntu Kylin 16.04, 18.04 and 20.04
Here you can see that all our language support is done on a long-term support version
Then, I would like to introduce to you one of our translation data
Because the localization of the operating system is a huge work
in the past practice, our translation coverage is currently more than 40%
Then, according to our own statistics
on Ubuntu and Ubuntu Kylin
there are nearly 150,000 and more than 172,000 translated data
The translation data here is mainly derived from a translation data tone of the Chinese language pack
The Chinese language packs we are comparing here are language-pack-zh-hans
and language-pack-zh-hans-base
Then the translations we completed were roughly 61100 on 16.04
and nearly 56,000 on 20.04
Then I would like to introduce a language pack support we provide
We provide a series of language packages
including kylin-language-pack-bo-cn
and kylin-language-pack-bo-cn-base, as well as an extra language pack
Here, kylin-language-pack-bo-cn is a virtual package
mainly to help apt to calculate a dependency of related language packages
It means that we only need to install this package
and it will automatically pull a base package, an extension package, and some other language setting packages
as well as support for the fonts we use
The words here in the kylin-language-pack-bo-cn-base package
It are mainly a translation file for all applications that use the Gettext translation file format to store
such as the PO and MO files
Then the extra package is mainly for applications that use the Qt multi-language support file format
to provide extended translation support
such as the TS and QM files
Then we can check a control file supported by our language package
Then its words were actually compiled and translated from a copy of a source package
Then we can take a look at the construction process of the package.
The construction is mainly aimed at a separate construction of PO and MO
And its support list is relatively complicated
Next, I will give a brief introduction to one of our development models in the past two years
our development model has crossed multiple data storage methods
Then all of our translation data are from the Chinese language pack as mentioned before
and then we use the Chinese language pack to construct a series of empty Tibetan-Chinese translation files
Then we imported these two parts of data into our git repository hosted on GitHub
and then exported a data table comparing Chinese and Tibetan through the git repository
This data table was constructed at the beginning
which is the stage0 part of the work I will talk about later
After we export the comparison table
our translator will translate this part of the comparison table to get a translated comparison table
and then we will import it into our git warehouse simultaneously
Then we also built a translation database based on this git repository
This translation database is on localhost
Then this translation database is mainly to provide a translated word match with itself.
We will give a brief introduction to this word self-match later in stage1
The same git repository and our Weblate platform provide a bidirectional synchronization support
The Weblate platform mainly provides a front-end interface editing support for translation
Then our git repository can generate our Tibetan language packages
which are the three language packs we just mentioned earlier
This part of the work can also be build automatically
Regarding stage0, we mainly describe the situation in the early stage of Tibetan-Chinese localization
Although in the 2020 generation, ubuntu
is a relatively popular release distro
But one of its development processes is for the university faculty and students who have just started to contribute to Ubuntu
It is said that there is a certain threshold
so at the beginning, we did not use ubuntu's development platforms like launchpad
and some of its patches and dpkg tools
At the beginning, I exported all the translated documents in the system into an Excel table for Chinese and English comparison
which is the comparison table we just mentioned
this table is mainly used so that people who are not familiar with the development tools of Ubuntu
can participate in the translation contribution as simply as possible
one of the main reasons why we did not use launchpad for translation work
was that it did not have a good Chinese interface support
and its interoperability was somewhat cumbersome
At that time we had not deployed our own Weblate service
so we used the git repository
and then exported the excel table to manage our translation data
There are about 30,000 translation data managed in this way
Our repositories are located on GitHub
and your can check our latest status in our GitHub repositories.
Here, one is on 16.04, and the other is on the hosting status of the translated files on 20.04
Then in the stage 1, we deployed our own self-hosted Weblate service
better synchronization with the repositories and an online translation service database
At this stage, we have built a local translation database
mainly for the convenience of storing all translated entries
On the basis of these translations, methods like Levenshtein
are used to make a vague match for the approximate translation based on the editing distance
Then in this way, we roughly added 10,000 translations
Of course, this part of the translation still needs manual review
Then I have a copy of the translation database locally
We can see that there are a total of 172,369 pieces of data
The amount of translated data in Tibetan is probably more than 40%
.It is a very large amount
and you can see the translation of it in Tibetan-Chinese
Then the fuzzy match we just said is
an improved method based on Levenshtein
It is different from the edit distance comparison of character strings
I myself call it the edit distance comparison based on Tibetan-Chinese syllables
The Tibetan-Chinese syllable here contains basic characters
powel, upper-added character, lower-added character, pre-added character, post-added character
A component part is a character
Then the words of one syllable are composed of seven characters at most
and the least words are composed of three to four characters
By changing a character-based approach to a syllable-based approach
we can filter out some interference from editing operations that have nothing to do with syllables
here is an explanation and support for the Tibetan-Chinese syllables
I would like to thank again for the theoretical support provided by Professor ཉི་མ་བཀྲ་ཤིས།  of Tibet University
The editing method of the Tibetan-Chinese syllables here is derived from a theoretical method of Tibetan-Chinese sorting
and then a series of finite-state machine is realized through his method
and then a simple parse of these things is carried out
Then in the stage 2, we started to use the Weblate platform to carry out an open source co-translation
and then at the same time build our language packages
Although we are talking about using an open source collaborative model,
our collaborative development is not distributed globally
Although it is not distributed all over the globe, it also spans thousands of kilometers and then connects every member of our team
Then you can visit our Weblate service at this website
From here, you can see that the proportion of Tibetan translation is 41%,
and then there are nearly 88,000 entries that are not translated
There are probably more than 500 components for all the components,
and more than 500 components cover most of the applications in the system
most of the key components,
like libc, glib and some applications of GNOME.
I installed an Ubuntu Kylin system integrated with the Tibetan-Chinese language package in my local machine
It was installed through QEMU
Let's take a look at the following
Here are just an installed system of Ubuntu Kylin 20.04
In fact, we have implemented a translation support for most of the applications, mainly applications of UKUI
and some GTK applications
Here we can use the UKUI control center to switch the language status of the current system
Like the words here, it provides a large number of Tibetan-Chinese language support
For the words here, we set Tibetan-Chinese
as the first supported language in this environment
and then the second supported language is Chinese, followed by English
when it comes to UKUI's control center
most of the translation of the control center has been almost completed
Although there are still some remaining unsupported parts
the relative usability has already been prepared
The translation of the setting interface is fully covered
Then, like some traditional gtk applications, such as Mate Terminal
there is also a complete Tibetan-Chinese language support
Then, when we open the terminal, we can briefly introduce
the Tibetan-Chinese translation support of some cli programs
such as the commonly used sudo
and the Tibetan-Chinese localization support on the password prompt
There are also some common commands like ls and df that also have some Tibetan-Chinese support
but they are not completely covered
Then, in the next words, you can take a look at UKUI's default file manager
and then there is also a nice support for Tibetan-Chinese
including support for some setting options and view settings.
Then there is some support like tag
And for GTK applications, in fact, like pluma
and Print Setting all have a complete Tibetan-Chinese language support.
Because this part of the function is the most commonly used function in daily life
so we also give priority to a localization support
There are also games like minesweeper,
and GTK games also have some simple Tibetan-Chinese support
And in addition to this, it is worth mentioning that GIMP
has also completed a highly completed Tibetan-Chinese translation support.
basically covering all the options like Tooltips and some options in the menu bar.
In addition to these commonly used GTK applications
we have also done a complete Tibetan-Chinese support for the applications in the entire UKUI desktop environment
For example, the tools we use daily, such as calculator
also have a preliminary Tibetan-Chinese language support
There is also UKUI Search, and UKUI video player
Here, the video player also has a localization support for the Tibetan-Chinese language on some settings
In this case, the degree of completion of translation is still relatively high
There is also a tool for hardware machine inspection provided by Ubuntu Kylin
It is Youker Assistanter
We have also done a lot of translation work on some of its hardware info
there is something worth mentioning here is the support of a Tibetan-Chinese input method we cooperated with Sogou
we provides a new Tibetan-Chinese input method.
The features include automatic association of syllables
and quick spelling of words
, etc
here are very grateful to Sogou for its support of promoting the localization of Ubuntu Kylin in Tibetan-Chinese
Then, a demonstration demo about the degree of support for Tibetan translation on Ukylin 20.04 will probably end here
If we follow up, I will introduce a plan for everyone to follow
Even though we have already had a good start in ubuntu as localization
there is still a lot of work we need to do in the future
We plan to further translate the translation of all entries in the entire Ubuntu
and then go to translate for more untranslated data
Then the second part is to promote a complete and pure open source of our project.
Because at the moment we can see that the protocol used in the git repository is still a proprietary license
Because we have not obtained a single authorization from all the translators involved
we are gradually pushing all the translators in to confirm their translation status
Then this part is the open source that we want to promote this project
Then one step further is to provide localized support for other ethnic minority languages in China
Like the words in our plan, there is support for localization of some minority languages in Manchu-Chinese language, Mongolian-Chinese language, Uyghur-Chinese language, and Zhuang-Chinese Language
thank you all for watching
In the end, I would like to thank again Professor ཉི་མ་བཀྲ་ཤིས། , Professor རིག་འཛིན་རྡོ་རྗེ། , Professor བསོད་ནམས་རྒྱ་མཚོ།
and Mr. འཇམ་དབྱངས་རྒྱལ། , Mr. བསམ་འཕེལ་ཚེ་རིང་།
for their great help in our Tibetan-Chinese localization work
Thank you all, bye