Let me introduce myself, my name is Kuriyanto. I am from Indonesia.
I am a teacher at SMK (Vocational School) Negeri 1 Kragilan.
Today I will discuss about Sinau-Bash.
Sinau-Bash is a program used to learn Bash language,
or program for learning Bash command.
About Bash
Bash is a shell-based programming language that is installed on Linux and Mac OS by default.
Bash itself is developed by the GNU Project and is licensed free.
About Sinau-Bash
Sinau-Bash itself is a simple program developed in the Bash language.
Sinau in Javanese means learning. If put together Sinau-Bash means learning Bash.
Sinau-Bash consists of three levels, the first is the easy level. This easy level when the answer is wrong then the answer will appear.
Level 2 is medium level, at this level if the answer is wrong then there is no correct answer information.
Hard level or difficult level will not show wrong answer information and will display the result when we are completed answering all questions from Sinau-Bash.
Sinau-Bash looks more or less like this. For now there are two languages provided, the first is Indonesian, and the second is English.
This is an example when we choose English.
You can download it from the address shown here.
I will show you how to download Sinau-Bash, run Sinau-Bash, and learn with Sinau-Bash.
We enter the link at https://github.com/kuriyantoadi/sinau-bash-ubucon.
We can click the code and then download the zip, later when it is downloaded, just look for the folder, there will be an install.sh file.
To run this install.sh command we can use the terminal.
We can right click here and then Open Terminal in our Sinau-Bash.
It's in the Sinau-Bash folder.
Now that I'm in the Sinau-Bash directory, let's check if we have the install.sh file.
I already have an install.sh file, then we can run it with the command ./install.sh, Enter.
Sinau-Bash looks like this.
Please select your language, there are two languages, Indonesian and English.
Initially it was developed only for Indonesian because the first time I made it, it was intended for vocational schools students
who will learn Linux server, so basically you have to learn Sinau-Bash first so you can proceed to learn server.
Now I have developed it to include English.
For those of you who are in Asia such as Malaysia, Japan, Korea, China, Pakistan, India, and you want to develop it
in the local language of your country, please feel free to email me and contribute to developing Sinau-Bash.
I give you an example to enter Sinau-Bash using English, we select 2 (two) then Enter.
Here we can write our names as participants. I wrote Kuriyanto, the reason is to try Sinau-Bash.
There are three levels, the first is easy, then medium, and hard.
We try easy level, and a question appears like this: "To open a zip file with the command?"
And you can write down the answer below. To open a zip file, the command is unzip, press Enter.
If your answer is correct it will say "Your answer is correct", this means we successfully answer the question.
And the next question, "To add a new user with the command ?"
adduser. This is the right one, let's try to enter the wrong answer.
For example, the question is "To enter a directory with the command ?" our answer is "ls" (should be cd or change directory), Enter.
There will be an error message, "Sorry your answer is wrong".
And the correct answer will be shown, the answer is cd or change directory.
Okay, this is easy level of Sinau-Bash. We'll try the medium level at a new tab.
We choose 2 and medium, Enter.
The question is "To create a belajar-bash directory you can enter the command ?"
The answer is "mkdir belajar-bash". This is the right answer.
The next question is "Command to give full user, group, and other access rights to files ?", the right answer is "chmod 777".
But we'll try to answer incorrectly, we will see if there will be an answer or not, we try only "chmod".
The answer is wrong, "Sorry your answer is wrong."
So if the answer is wrong, there will be no correct answer below. Unlike the easy level (easy), the correct answer will be shown.
Next we'll try the hard level.
We have a server with IP address 10.78.12.1, how to access the server remotely with SSH?
The command is "ssh 10.78.12.1".
In the hard level of Sinau-Bash, the answer will not be shown whether it is right or wrong.
And the previous questions will disappear, and the result will be shown later after we finish answering all the questions from Sinau-Bash.
For example, we finish the easy one first.
When finished, the result will appear like this.
I have answered all of the questions in 375 seconds with easy questions and my score is 90.
So we have answered 20 questions, there are 20 questions per level and each question is worth 5 point. I have 2 questions that answered incorrectly.
For Sinau-Bash, although the questions are the same, each time the questions will be different because they are randomized.
Because the questions are randomized, there are 60 possibilities of randomization, we can repeat the study with Sinau-Bash with a different order of questions,
and it will make our memory of Bash basics more convenient.
Any questions so far?
Thank you for watching my material on Sinau-Bash. If you are interested in Sinau-Bash, you can download Sinau-Bash and learn Sinau-Bash.
For those of you who live abroad, especially from Asia, if you want to develop the Sinau-Bash program,
I am open if you want to contribute, develop and provide Sinau-Bash for people to learn. Thank you.