Today, I would like to talk about Ubuntu use case on Laptops and Raspberry Pis.
for Desktop users.
And also I'd like to talk about how manage them.
What are best practice, and how we should do.
I'm Masafumi Ohta, now leading RaspberryPI User Group in Japan.
I would love to introduce myself.
I have started RaspberryPi User Group in Japan since 2012.
I also volunteering for RaspberryPi Foundation.
What I am mainly doing for is
help their business in Japan.
Now, I'm also helping expanding the market that includes out of Japan,
Such as China, Taiwan.
This is another self introduction
in RaspberryPi Official Forum.
It's hosted the "Japanese" category in the Raspberry Pi Offical forum
You can read my post from Raspberry PI Official Site
And please check "Japanese" category.
I'm appreciate that if you check out.
Here is today's agenda.
Do you love Ubuntu Desktop? And is it useful?
Should we preserve dualboot with Windows?
Hacks about UEFI and SD Cards.
And other Tips.
Can we use Raspberry Pi as Ubuntu Desktop?
I'd like to introduce Raspberry Pi with Ubuntu in the last topic
Okay, as first,
Do You Love Ubuntu Desktop?
Why I'd like to talk about,
Here is post by my firend in Taiwan, tha't picture in Facebook.
In past,
He, my firend, said "Freedom is Important"
And he also declare that he don't have any needs of Microsoft Office.
"Open Source is great."
So he told that, "We should use Debian/GNU Linux"
However, now, I recheck his opinion, he said that..... "macOS is best"
And he told that, "MacBook Pro is amazing."
From realistic viewpoint, we can't avoid this type of matter,
When we use Ubuntu Linux as Desktop,
we should consider that this point of view, the problem is,
Using Ubuntu Desktop are, it is like building blocks with Lego,
we should build our own custom one-off machine
I guess we should evaluate this point of view,
When we use Windows, we may install apps and set some settings
We should build our environment from Vanilla much more than Window - installing Operating System, and install many applications, describe configs...
and many setups are needed. It's time to take many tasks.
And more
I guess We should take more time than expected
using Ubuntu.
We might meet unexpected things,
We should accept something trade-offs.
From this viewpoint, frankly speaking,
we need patience that same as builing Logo blocks.
It's also fun both builing and using that,
builing our own environment is great experience,
It's my own first prototype environment with GPD Pocket 2 (Handheld PC)
It's Linux Desktop,
I installed on the SDCard,
lately I replaced that
Here is my latest  environment,
This is built with gpd Pocket 2 2021, minor updates
I have directly installed to SSD
By the way,
There are problem that GPD Pocket got hot,
especially bace face has high temperature.
Because Core M3 consume electrical power and make heats.
This picture is my hack, pasted heatthink plates and cooling that.
However, if you can accept this point, it become great gadget.
It has extremely portable,
I can read e-mails and have web surfines in train,
Suspend/Resume is fast enough if you install Ubuntu into SSD.
so I am sure that it's very useful.
Anyway, return to topic about should we preserve Windows.
I think that we have just one reason,
if we update BIOS/UEFI with safety and easy way, we should use windows.
GPD Pocket has windows application that can easily update BIOS/UEFI.
Just click and wait, it's easy and fast.
We have another approach, BIOS/UEFI has built-in update interface,
we can update firmware with that interface.
We have alternative solutions,
extracting from firmware archive, and getting binary
after that, we can update via BIOS/UEFI menu.
And another approach is, using USB bootable OS
and upgrade from that OS.
Unfortunately, most safest way updating is to do with Windows.
So, we might preserve Windows.
And also, we have another reason for using Windows.
In realistic use scnenarios, we need Zoom, Microsoft Office,
and some Security softwares.
And BIOS Updater, many chattools, these are firendly in Windows
and Linux's aren't so.
In using Zoom, I should consider
about some factors, AI Camera functions
aren't workbale on Linux. So I must use Windows.
That's huge gap between Linux and Windows,
and IMHO this is vendor side issue,
Maintenance and QA are should be provided on Windows,
it's by-design.
In this gadget, I have to talk about con
Firstly, we, linux users is too much annoyed slow speeds on SD cards because we can't use internal SSD as main storage.
And also, it's easy to corrupt,
we will see many bad sectors day by day.
I planed that using USB Memory but
Performance is limited by USB port,
it's unavoidable.
And also it's limtited by total capacity of
USB logical tree.
USB Port also used to Ethernet connections,
it consumes bandwidth and causes USB speeds down.
So, when we use some applications,
By Limited disk bandwidth, we should manage that.
And also, frankly saying, internal disk is really fast.
Here is result of benchmark,
Both microSD card's and internal disk's,
It's KDiskMark, CrystalDiskMark-like benchmark software
We can get insight that random access is etremely slow.
So we should consider how mitigate that, here.
First, I would talk tips of using microSD,
with my experience about GPD Pocket,
I can't use suspend because Resume take many
time and have stability issue.
So I think that Hybernation is better using SD-Card.
Also I used memcache (memdisk) as cache.
It can make virtual storage
that uses some of memory
I am sure using virtual storage is mandatory
for Games, Browsers, MUAs,
because these applications
have massive writes,
And also these write operations
require speed.
So I estimated that virtual storage
is mandatory factor.
This is tough point when using microSD.
Okay, let's start diving deep to this.
UEFI and SD Card hacks, with have a fun.
These're UEFI's limitation, and...
it may be surprised we can see many "Locked" features.
"Unlocked" gadget is rare cases,
dominant exceptional cases are gaming Laptop.
Gaming Laptop needs optimization, thus these are "Unlocked".
Return to "Locked" cases, we can't change VT-d enablement and CPU frequency.
Sometimes these aren't displayed and also disabled.
Especially, disabling VT-d is critital for virtualization use cases.
So I asked vendors about these "Locked".
Vendors said: "It's for safety use".
"For preventing accidents, it should be "Locked" and "not displayed"".
In these cases, I tried to request
for getting special "Unlocked" UEFI images.
Results are depended by-vendors,
some vendor provided that.
In many cases, Japanese vendors
didn't provide custom image.
And Chinese vendors are negotiable, but it's just subjective tends.
Okay, I'd talk about SD Cards hacks.
You might have experience of installation,
And if so, install to SD Card itself isn't difficult.
Difficult point is, we should consider SD Cards themselves.
For examle, "Which vendor is better"
Write cycle limits are per-Vendor matter.
And also you might know, in many cases, we can't use "trim" them.
As a result, we have no way
to reduce write cycles.
It means that we can easily attenpt and then exceed
write-cycles-limits of them.
Also we should know that
SD Cards are easily cause data corruptions.
And ocaissionary the Card itself become not functional.
So we should clarify the excess caused by broken media,
or just data corruption.
And also we should decide which is better,
replace SD Card, execute fsck, and more.
Installing Windows to SD Card may be the best way if we could
However, Windows can be only installed to internal PCIe Storage
Due to boot ralated limiation.
So we can't install Windows to SD Card.
Anyway, SD Cards didn't have "trim"
So we should consider how reduce write operations.
And also we should check data corruptions.
Let's considering how manage when
SD Cards itself become not functional state.
From my exeperience, dominant cases are
"becoming Read Only"
So first approach is "touch" command.
touch can detect
When you meet "Read Only" issue,
deletion and replaces are too early, next step is...
Boot from Live USB, and use gparted
and execute chkdsk
and chkdisk may recover the issue
In many cases, we can resolve the issue
because it's special trick.
I try to explain what's happen,
it's my guess, some of SD Cards have
specific behavior.  e.g. Transcend's.
After a certain numbers of read operations,
they will be turned to "Read Only",
as safety mechanisms.
And chkdsk will recover that.
After that, we can reuse SD Cards till next limit.
These behavior are probably "By-design"
safety mechanisms.
For controlling these behavior,
chkdsk is first step of trouble shooting.
And if we can't recover "Read Only" with this approach,
we should consider next step.
Next Step is, getting new SD Cards,
and starting full copy with "dd" command.
Copying with "dd" is time consuming,
but most reliable approach.
This page has some tuning approachs to avoid
overloading to SD Cards,
Create memdisk working directory
and using as /tmp
Also I created working directory with memdisk,
and here is a Firefox tweaks,
that will use ramdisk /tmp.
For your information about SD Cards issues,
this is famous articles in Rasberry Pi.
Author is Peter Stevens,
who provides Rasbperry Pi Hosting Service, "mythic beasts"
They have great knowledge
about SD Cards handling in real,
In begining, they tryed hosting service
that uses SD Cards,
And they meet many issues,
this is useful.
And based on this knowledge, we should
understand how SD Cards are fragile.
Okay, next.
AntiVirus softwares,
I tested Dr.Web and ESET
Dr. Web consumed 100% CPU in scan,
even if I used SSD.
GPD Pocket doesn't have enough CPU power,
so we should consider that.
For avoiding issue, scheduling
that to idle time,
I think scheduling is maneagable
but bit tough.
ESET doesn't consume CPU power.
Per AntiVirus Softwares, someone consumes
machine resources.
So we should consider
selection with tests
For detecting, I found
some key symptoms
When automatic updates, I can't use apt
because Dr.Web consumes whole CPUs.
I feel that it's not usable in my use case.
Next, Grub settings,
In real Desktop usecase,
we should use dual boot with Windows,
And if we erase Windows and
install ubuntu directly to internal SSD,
It can cause issue.
In my case, I can't boot system itself,
no boot screen, no signal.
For solving the issue, AskUbuntu and other
articles may help you.
For Linux and Linux dual booting,
it means that you used Linux in SD Cards,
And plan to install another Linux
into internal storage.
For it cases, you might
meet another issues.
If one updates kernel related packages,
it will re-create Grub environment.
and it can affect other side Linux
As a result, one side needs
another side for booting.
For reparing, you might need
grub-install or boot repair tools.
In My case, SD Card's side re-create grub,
and Grub require SD Card side's,
so if I lost SD Card,
my GPD Pocket became unbootable.
For fixing it, Grub menu has a way
to select internal ssd,
After boot up, I re-create
Grub from internal SSD, problem gone.
For avoiding boot issue, we should
pay attention for Grub related things.
And here is related articles
when I met issue.
Is Rasberry Pi useful or not?
This is Ubuntu's official page,
and we have many Raspberry Pi images.
We have both 32-bit and 64bit
ubuntu 21.04 images
Ubuntu is now one of offical image. And, the images are
evaluated by engineers of Rasbperry Pi Foundation
It's appreciable point for you.
And of course these images
work well in Raspberry Pi 400 (JP)
It works in 64 bit and
I can input with Input Method (Kana input)
It's useful.
Next, I'd like to provide
line up of Rasberry Pi,
with information
about capability of ubuntu
Raspberry Pi3 is mainstream product
and of course Ubuntu is available.
Raspberry Pi4, I assume that
many peoples want to use container with Ubuntu Server
However, 8GB model is a really few stock now,
it may be improved in November.
So please stay tuned
with 4GB Model and others.
And, I would recommend to use Compute Module,
I would ask you to try.
Because it can connect many devices via PCI Express.
And also it has HDMI and others, you can use it as Desktop via I/O board
So let's enjoy and make some with your great idea.
Some of users are trying to create "Hand Held" PC.
Let's try such approachs and others.
I am really sorry that Compute Module remains USB2.0 because of the resources on SoC
And, Akkie, our community member, tested many devices
with PCIe connectivity.
Notable point is, both 10GbE and NVMe work well.
the most important point of Compute Module is,
RTC support available for it.
So we can build it for Embedded and Laptop.
And you can use it as Desktop.
btw, next is Rasberry Pi 400, Pi 400 is...
It has faster CPU and well designed heat sinks.
also it's fanless.
It's inspired by retro PCs, Commodore 64 and BBC Micro. Eben's hobby.
It's designed for education.
2nd batch included some of localized versions, for Japan and India.
localized versions for other countries will be supported but no ETAs.
So please check Rasberry Pi official page.
And official Twitter will provide information.
Okay, next is roadmap,
Some of roadmaps are leaked by founder Eben in Tom's Hardware.
For that, fundamentally,
We met semiconductor shortage,
and we cannot plan 4a and 5 at right now.
So no one can get new products untill fullfilled.
and if you can't wait, I'd like to point what should you check,
Return to Raspberry Pi's philosophy,  down-compatible,
for children, and have fun, these are great hint.
Also some of interviews and Github will have leak :)
Please check these places for getting latest information.
At last, I would talk "one more thing".
I have told that at many conferences,
We're calling your Raspberry Pi project.
What is suiting to requirement,
We have MagPi, the official Raspberry Pi Magazine,
We want to introduce your project as MagPi's articles.
There are many prospected articles in the world,
Of course, MagPi is magazine in UK, so
So dominant are in Europe and Africa.
Now, bit increased China and India's
However, it's still limited in the globe.
So,
We need more articles from other places, such as Korea, Taiwan, Hong-Kong, Macau, Vietnam and other places.
We want to meet and introduce great projects from diverse areas.
So we're appreciate that you will try / submit / contact us.
For example,
Here is my mediations,
This article is provided from Taiwan,
Maker is Penk Chen,
He provided "CutiePie".
And he works for Qt, and this handheld has rich UI.
It bumped into editor of MagPi, and
And he has intent to meet Penk Chen,
So I mediate both editor and Penk Chen, result is here.
I also introduced projects in Japan,
Here is VInyard Kikushima, Winery usecase by Mr.Kikushima.
In this winery, he uses Raspberry Pi
and getting many data from sensors.
Automated system changes volume of pesticides
What is need,
Too many pesticides will corrupt deliciousness of wine.
So he want to decrease them.
However, zero pesticides isn't realistic,
challange is, getting "lower limit" by sensors.
Okay, at last, it is not known exactly why, it's me.
I have dream that I would introduce Asia-wide projects,
not limited in Japan
I want to introduce many projects in various area,
I'm discussing with many open source communities,
and providing showcases.
Because I believe it shouldn't limit to Japan
I have been doing so,
China, Taiwan, Korea, Vietnam, Indonesia, Thailand.....and others,
I want to see many projects from many area.
So if you want to introduce your project.
Please feel free to reach out to me.
As conclusion,
Using Ubuntu Desktop is fun, but it likes Lego.
We should never forget it,
You should pay some time, not easy way.
If it's not feasible for usecase,
We should install to SD Card and use as sub desktop.
and use Windows as primary.
I would like to reiterate that.
And we should review Pros/Cons of
Internal SSD and microSD.
Considering trade-off is mandatory.
And also, we should understant that
how SD Card works as boot device.
And, For Rasbberry Pi, Ubuntu is official and 64bit.
Raspberry Pi OS 64 bit is currently trial phase.
64 bit suse is already official phase.
AFAIK, only suse and Ubuntu
are official phase with 64 bit support.
And if you have great project,
absolutely, please keep in touch with me.
Mail, Twitter, Facebook, Linkedin,
and other approaches are welcome.
Please let me know with any contacts.
Thank you for your time.
okay, just 30 minutes.
Have a nice day! See you all.